Guide to the James Henry Burton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Henry Burton papers
1845-1950
1845-1893
MS 117
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.75
(9 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, diaries, notebooks, clippings, printed matter and a draft history of the Richmond Armory which he headed from 1861 to 1862. Included also are notes on machinery and a British patent for small fire-arms.
Burton, James Henry, 1823-1894
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edwin Pugsley, 1953, 1958, and 1962. Gift of Eugenia Scheffel, 1998.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence and other papers available on microfilm (2 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM3.
Scope and Contents
The Colonel James H. Burton Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, photographs, plans, and miscellaneous items spanning from 1845 to 1950.
Biographical / Historical
Colonel James H. Burton (1823-1894), after he had been educated at Westchester Academy, Pennsylvania, entered a Baltimore machine shop at the age of sixteen. In 1844, he took employment in the rifle works of the United States armory at Harper's Ferry, was appointed foreman in 1845 and master armorer shortly thereafter. In 1855, he accepted the post of chief engineer of the Royal Small Arms Factory, Enfield, near London, and did not return to Virginia until 1861. In June of that year, Burton was commissioned a Lieutenant Colonel in the Ordinance Department of the Virginia State Militia and placed in charge of the State Armory by Governor John Letcher with instructions to arrange for the removal of all machinery captured at Harper's Ferry and place it in position for use. Within ninety days, Colonel Burton had the machinery at work in Richmond producing rifles of standard United States patterns.
The following September, Burton was appointed superintendent of arms by President Jefferson Davis with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. During the summer of 1863, the Confederate Government ordered Burton to Europe on State Department business. He did not return to the United States for three years and only then after having received an amnesty from President Johnson.
As a private citizen, he returned to England in 1871 to take direction of a Leeds firm manufacturing arms for the Russian Government. He returned to Virginia in 1873.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Firearms; Science; Europe; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries; Engineers; Burton, James Henry, 1823-1894; Confederate States of America. Army ( Ordnance and ordnance stores)
- Inventory, 1845-1950
  - Correspondence
    - 1845-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1862-1893 (Box 2)
  - Letterbooks, 1863, 1865-1866 (Box 3)
  - Plans of firearms and ammunition, 1852-1859, 1872-1873, undated (Box 3)
  - Draft, "History of Richmond Armory", 1893 (Box 3)
  - Diaries
    - 1855-1859 (Box 3)
    - 1859-1863, 1865, 1867 (Box 4)
    - 1868, 1872, 1875 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks
    - 1855-1866, 1888-1893 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Scrapbook, 1852-1860 (Box 6)
    - Photographs of James Burton, the Macon Armory, and unidentified persons and buildings, [1860?]-1928 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1860-1893 (Box 6)
    - James Hall: "Report upon the Property of the Empire State Iron and Coal Company, of Georgia", 1866 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence concerning James Burton, 1928-1950, undated (Box 6)
    - Notes concerning James Burton, machinery, and related subjects, 1860-1940, undated (Box 6)
    - Frank E. Vandiver: "A Sketch of Efforts Abroad to Equip the Confederate Armory at Macon," Georgia Historical Quarterly, 1944 (Box 6)
    - British patent issued for an improvement in the manufacture of barrels for small fire-arms, 1859 (Box 6)
  - Plans, drawings, and maps
    - Confederate States Armory, Macon, Georgia
      - Front elevation or view from Macon & Western Railroad, 21" x 98", 1864 March 23 (Box 7)
      - Design of Dwelling House for Mr. Herrington Mast. Machinist, 30 1/4" x 34 1/2", Undated (Box 7)
      - Design of cast iron ventilator for front building & wings, James A. Burton, Supt., 13 1/4" x 30 1/4", 1864 March 23 (Box 7)
      - Ground plan of basement story. Central Office, 10" x 14 3/4", 1863 May 5 (Box 7)
    - Map of Southwestern Part of City of Macon
      - Shows location of Confedrate States Armory and proposed connection of Armory track with Macon & Western Railroad signed A. Schwaab, CE, 14 3/4" x 18", 1863 December (Box 7)
      - Shows land purchased for Confederate States Armory by Col. Burton, Superintendent Surveyed by A. Schwaab, Civ. Eng., 23" x 24", 1864 April (Box 7)
      - Shows land purchased for Confederate States Armory by Col. Burton, Superintendent Surveyed by A. Schwaab, Civ. Eng., 21" x 22 3/4", 1864 April (Box 7)
      - Shows location of Confederate States Armory and proposed connexion of Armory Track with Macon & Western Railroad. Aug. Schwaab, CE, 15" x 16", 1863 December (Box 7)
    - Alteration of 2 screw drilling machines for facing striker nut (+B rifle) Order 528B full size, 26" x 39", Undated (Box 7)
    - General Store House 202 (ft.)/8 in. x 40 ft. 2 Stories High, 16 1/2" x 39", Undated (Box 7)
    - Cast iron base of column for main building of new armory. Jas. A. Burton, Supt. C. S., Armory, Macon, Ga., 22 3/4" x 30 1/4", 1864 March 23 (Box 7)
    - Design arrangement of lightning conductors (labeled on verso: General ground plans of roofs B), 22" x 29", Undated (Box 7)
    - General Ground Plan of roofs of Confederate States Armory to be erected in the city of Macon, made for the purpose of (labeled on verso: General ground plans of roofs A), 26 1/2" x 29", Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled (labeled on verso: #3), 29 1/2" x 36 1/2", Undated (Box 7)
    - Untitled, 3 pieces of one floor plan, (labeled on verso: 1, 2, 3), 1 - 29" x 36 1/2", 2 & 3 - 30" x 36 1/2", Undated (Box 7)
    - Vertical cross - nos - Main Work Shops, Detail of roof ridge, 19 3/4" x 28 3/4", Undated (Box 7)
    - Confederate States Armory at Macon, GA. General Groundplan, 3 pieces, 1 - 22" x 39", 2 - 30" x 40", 3 -30" x 39, Undated (Box 7)
  - Oversize, 1864-1888, undated (Box 8)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-111
  - Letterbooks, 1866-1873
    - 1866 August 2-1867 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1867 June 22-1868 sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1868 September 3-1872 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1872 February 17-1873 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - 1873 March 14-September 14 (Box 2, Folder 6)